A Guide to the Population Council records, Karen Morrell Fundraising Files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 16 FA1437
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Karen Morrell Fundraising Files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 16
1964-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
Morrell, Karen
FA1437
0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter-size document box.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Population Council was founded by John D. Rockefeller 3rd in 1952 to undertake "significant activities in the broad field of population." Its goal has been to bring about a reduction in the number of births that occur in the world. In its early years, the business of the Population Council was conducted by a Demographic Division and a Biomedical Division. Through its Demographic Division, the Council sought to document what it conceived to be an overpopulation problem threatening many areas of the world. To accomplish this purpose, the Division facilitated research on the economic, social, and psychological factors which affect the growth and decline of human population. This Council-assisted research effort was conducted not only by staff of the Demographic Division but also by other institutions and scholars, some of whom received Council grants and fellowships and some of whom received informal advice and consultation on how to design and execute studies.
The Biomedical Division, which, beginning in 1959, occupied a laboratory at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now The Rockefeller University), has conducted pure and applied research on plant, animal, and human reproductive physiology and on the development, the physiological action, and the safety and effectiveness of contraceptive methods. The Council facilitated similar types of medical research by non-Council scientists at other institutions by giving grants and fellowships for such research. The Council's biomedical research and its support for research by non-Council scientists were instrumental in the development of the modern intrauterine coil and the birth control pill.
In about 1960, the scope of Population Council activities expanded. The Council began to render practical and technical aid to foreign nations. Beginning in that year, the Demographic Division, in addition to supervising research, became involved in Pakistan's family planning program, extending practical and technical aid in organizing and running a national family planning program. By 1964 the Council's Demographic Division had assisted in organizing family planning programs in South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand, Tunisia, and Turkey. In that year, the Council created the Technical Assistance Division. This division, in ensuing years, continued the assistance of the Council in the countries where it had already become involved and also helped start and run programs in India, Morocco, the Philippines, and Puerto Rico.
An underlying aim of the Council's grant programs has been to encourage the development and growth of institutions that would promote family planning programs. To this end, the Council has given grants and advice to various universities and research centers for starting and upgrading programs for demographic and biomedical training and research programs; has assisted the United Nations to set up and expand regional Demographic Training and Research Centres in Bombay, India, Santiago, Chile, and Cairo, Egypt; has worked with the Ford Foundation on family planning programs in Pakistan, India, and North Africa.
In addition to rendering technical aid and sponsoring research, the Council has undertaken several complementary public relations efforts. To reach the general populations of the United States and of foreign nations, Council officers have worked to inform the mass media about population issues and to encourage magazine articles, movies, and books dealing with population matters. Council officers and representatives have also made trips and prepared reports to convince various foreign government leaders of the importance and the desirability of promulgating family planning programs. In addition, Council officers participated in and helped organize and finance conferences for demographers and medical scientists active in population work.
The Population Council has obtained its financial support through large contributions. The Ford and Rockefeller Foundations and the Rockefeller Brothers Fund have been the principal institutional supporters of the Council. John D. Rockefeller 3rd has been the single most significant individual backer of the Council.
Arrangement
Original order is maintained, as received.
Scope and Contents
The Karen Morrell Fundraising files are comprised of correspondence and memos with reports and other supportive background documentation.
Scope and Contents
The Karen Morrell Fundraising files are comprised of correspondence and memos with reports and other supportive background documentation.
- Karen Morrell Fundraising Files, 1964-1980; 16
  - The New York Community Trust, Community Funds, Inc., 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The McKnight Foundation, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Leverhulme Trust, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Kroc Foundation, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Robert Sterling Clark Foundation, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - China Medical Board, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eppley Foundation for Research, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Bush Foundation, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Murry D. Buxbaum, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Ciba Foundation, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Goodhill Foundation, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Fannie E. Rippel Foundation, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Olin Foundation, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Nuffield Foundation, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Max C. Fleischmann Foundation, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Charles E. Merrill Trust, 1964-1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)